in the past few sessions we've been
looking at 17th century thinking which
we have already described as the Age of
Reason
or the movement called rationalism
well if
the 17th century was the age of
rationalism in the history of Western
thought we look at the 18th century as
the age of empiricism
now I realize that the term empiricism
is not a word that everybody is familiar
with it's not one of those normal terms
that we use in our daily conversation
but the the dispute between the
philosophers of the 18th century
particularly in Great Britain with the
Continental rationalists of the 17th
century was principally a debate over
epistemology and we've already learned
that epistemology is the science of
knowing
now
often because I am a representative and
advocate of what I call rational
Christianity I have to hear the
criticism again and again that I am a
rationalist and I am always quick to
point out that there's a difference
between being rational and being a
rationalist and the differences in those
last three letters and as soon as you
put an ism on the end of a perfectly
harmless word you enter into a whole
life and world view as I say there's a
big difference between being human and
being a humanist and I want to say that
Christianity is rational that doesn't
mean that I embrace rationalism or that
I'm a rationalist but that's only part
of the problem
because the term rationalism
is used in more than one way in our
culture
in fact I would suggest
that it's it's used in at least two
dramatically different ways the first is
the way in which we've already seen it
namely referring to a philosophy that
puts the Primacy that is the accent and
the emphasis upon the mind and rational
deduction as the chief and most
important way that we come to a
knowledge of Truth as distinguished from
empiricism
which teaches that the principal way
that we come to a knowledge of the truth
is not through rational deduction or
through intellectual speculation but
rather by working on the brute data the
facts that we encounter in our sensory
experience the empiricist is one who
says that the way I learn is by seeing
hearing tasting touching and so on
now in that regard the empiricists were
not irrationalists they were not opposed
to the proper use of reason but rather
they're simply saying that in the
knowing process
the way in which knowledge is gained is
first of all through experience and we
still have minds and the minds have to
work with the information and the data
we get from our senses from our sense
organs
but the mind is not first in the order
of knowing rather senses are first in
the order of knowing but another way in
which the term rationalism is used
is with respect to
the question of the ultimate source of
Truth
the Christian believes
that though our faith is rational
the ultimate source for our knowledge
and for truth is divine revelation
so that the Supreme way of knowing is by
being informed by God himself
now the 18th century thinkers who bought
into
empiricism in the at least some of them
were also called rationalists not
because they saw a Primacy of Reason
over the senses but because they wanted
to limit their understanding of religion
to that which can be known simply by
natural reason
reflecting upon the experience that we
encounter in the universe
and not being dependent upon some kind
of Supernatural source of Revelation
such as we would find in sacred
scripture
so that school of thinkers is also
sometimes called
rationalists or rationalism meaning by
that that
knowledge is not based upon some kind of
faith in a received content of
Revelation from God but rather whatever
knowledge of God we have is limited to
Natural reason and science
discovering what it can in the ordinary
Common Sense Arena of knowledge now
there's still even a third way in which
the term rationalism is used
and I just mentioned that briefly in
passing and that is when they when you
speak of rationalism with a capital R
and we think back to the 19th century
movement of which uh Frederick Hegel was
The prominent thinker and he saw all of
reality being an unfolding of reason
with a capital R for him there really is
Divine reason the reason itself becomes
God
now when I talk about rational
Christianity I don't mean any one of
those three things I'm simply saying
that the content of the Christian faith
is intelligible it is coherent we can
understand it with our minds but now
let's like let's give some attention now
to this movement that takes place in the
18th century that we call empiricism
there were many important thinkers
during this time but certainly the most
important early thinker in this movement
was John Locke now you've probably heard
of John Locke even if you've heard
nothing of the history of Western
philosophy
because among other things Locke was
very much concerned with political
philosophy with political Theory and
much of his thinking on how governments
should be established and shaped had an
enormous influence on the founding
fathers of the American Republic such as
Thomas Jefferson
it was locky in theory of represent
representative government of government
by checks and balance and so on that had
such an impact in the latter part of the
18th century
but I'm not really going to go into his
political philosophy here because he's
also very important in the history of
theoretical thought for his epistemology
now just a bit of background on Locke he
was born
in 1632 and died in 1704 so that tells
us that most of his life and work took
place in the 17th century and yet he
forms the key transition from 17th
century rationalism to 18th century
empiricism he was a graduate of Oxford
and unlike the seventh other 17th
century rationalists whom almost all of
them were mathematicians or physicists
John Locke was a practicing physician
and he had very little time
for speculative philosophy
he said I have to make a decision when
somebody comes to me with an ailment
of what is the actual physical cause of
their illness that may be fatal
he said I can't just sit around and do
math and speculate about what could
conceivably be wrong but I have to begin
to probe to test even perhaps to do
surgery to find out with my senses
what's wrong here and how can we go
about fixing it
so in one sense
in a very real sense
John Locke was a common sense thinker
and he was much more concerned about our
common encounter with reality rather
than on rational
rational speculation
he was also an outspoken
enemy
to a hyper form of rationalism that
became known as conceptualism
well
conceptualism in its most crude form
came to the conclusion
that any idea
that can be conceived of in the mind
as being rational
must exist
in reality
because
the rational
is real
now be careful here that's not the same
thing as saying whatever is real
is rational
but rather whatever is rational
is real
so that if we can have a rational
concept for example of a unicorn
there must be a unicorn out there in
reality
as I said this is an extreme form of
rationalism
and part of it was born out of the
incredible advances that were being made
as I've mentioned before in the new
discoveries in the scientific world
where it was the mathematicians who were
The Cutting Edge thinkers who were the
ones who were saying our math indicates
that if we point our telescope at this
point in outer space there should be a
planet there or there should be a moon
there and they would point the telescope
and voila just as their mathematical
projections had anticipated there was
the reality
and so there became so much confidence
given to mathematics because of what
math had been able to achieve in
breaking through to New Dimensions of
learning that some went to the extreme
positions said well if it's
mathematically conceivable
it must actually exist out there
and uh
John Locke thought that was nonsense he
said that the mind has ability to be
imaginative to create fiction where you
combine an idea from here and an idea
from here you take the idea of redness
and you take the idea of polar bearness
and you can conceive of a fiery bright
red polar bear that doesn't mean there
is such a thing as a fiery bright red
polar bear and so he wanted to bring
philosophy back to Earth and force
philosophy to deal with the real
with what is really out there
and so one of the most important things
that
that Locke gave to us
was a theory of Truth he's not the only
person who's held this Theory but his
name is often linked with it
which is called the correspondence
theory
of Truth
and in simple terms the correspondence
theory of Truth says this
that truth
is that
which corresponds to
reality
that's a very simple idea
in our day and age
it's an idea
that is under attack every moment
because this concept of Truth says that
truth
is that which is real
and it is therefore objective
that what is really out there is not
dependent upon how I feel about it or
even how I perceive it
because I am not the author of truth I
am not the one who creates reality I
encounter reality
I meet reality and I have to respond to
things that are really out there apart
from me
and the pursuit of Science and the
pursuit of Truth is the pursuit of
discovering the real
rather than the imaginary or the
fictional
today we hear people embracing
relativism and subjectivism saying truth
is whatever I think it is or whatever I
want it to be
the lock would have no time for that
kind of thinking that would make real
science impossible because the world
would then be according to GARP that is
it would be one thing for you another
thing for you and a third thing for you
whatever you want it to be as I've told
the story before about the woman I was
discussing the existence of God with and
she said to me
do you believe in God and I said yes and
she said does that do you find that
meaningful yes do you pray yes do you
sing hymns yes and all of that
she says well if you find all that stuff
satisfying
and meaningful she sounds like a modern
day Pascal
she says then for you God exists
but for me
I don't find any meaning in worship or
in singing or in praying that stuff
leaves me cold
I'm not interested in it
I don't feel any psychological need for
it
and so for me there is no God
and I said well what I'm not talking to
you about here is religion
and its emotional impact on me or on you
I'm talking about the question of the
existence of a being whose exists apart
from you and apart from me
who if there is no such being in reality
all of my praying all of my singing all
of my emotional satisfaction surrounding
it does not have the power to create
such a being
and likewise if you're indifferent
toward that being or cold toward that
being and they're turned off by prayer
and music and all the rest your personal
attitude toward this being does not have
the power to destroy him
I said we have to at some point Come the
question is there a god out there or not
is there an objective reality that we
call God now see Lockwood understand
what I'm saying here he's saying truth
is not preference
truth is not a subjective inclination in
an individual's heart but truth is that
which is real
real apart from me but then again his
question is
how do we get to truth
how do we come to a knowledge of Truth
well the one Latin phrase that is
closely connected with John Locke many
people are familiar with this even if
they've never studied the history of
philosophy they've perhaps heard of this
little phrase tabula rasa
which means blank tabula Tab tablet or
blank slate
here's what Locke was getting at with
the tabula rasa concept
he said every person is born
with a mind that has no information
in it
it's a blank slate a blank tablet
nothing has been written on it in a word
there are no innate ideas
an innate idea would be an idea that you
were born with now remember Plato
he says the soul carries into this
incarnation
sum total of all knowledge that all
knowledge is innate and the whole
process of learning is simply trying to
recall or bring to the surface that
which is already there it's inherent
that's in the soul it's in the mind at
Birth
for Locke there are no innate ideas
no truths that are inherent in the mind
remember Descartes
he wanted to find those clear and
distinct ideas
where he would say the idea that a
triangle has three sides is an innate
idea it is a priori it comes before
experience
for Locke
Locke says no to the ah priori and
insists on the ah posteriori
namely that all knowledge comes after
experience
and everything is based upon this blank
tablet you're born with it
but then you have a sense perception
and that's the First Data bit you see
your mother where you see a dog you have
a sensation a perception or you feel
something or you taste something or you
hear something and those experiences are
then recorded on your brain
and all of your knowledge that you
acquire in your lifetime
all of that knowledge is acquired
through this constant series of
experience and in this sense
you are learning
every second that you are awake in your
lifetime
you're learning whether you want to
learn or not learn you never stop going
to the school of experience
and even if you graduate from the
University or wherever that's not the
end of your learning
every new experience is a new learning
experience as more data is now being
introduced to the mind
so for Locke all knowledge begins with
particulars
individual data bits of experience
and the abstract Concepts that we call
the universals or the generalities
where we speak of mankind or
squirrel nests or chair Ness or whatever
they are simply the result of multiple
individual experiences that we have now
the mind has no innate
knowledge for Locke but it does have
an innate ability
let's make that distinction
there's no born with content of
knowledge in your mind
but the mind as an organism
has a built-in innate ability
an ability to receive the data of those
Impressions or Sensations from your
sense experience
but the brain is not just or the mind is
not just passively receiving experiences
the mind also has the power or the
ability to be active
the mind
can
select it can combine it can abstract
and it can relate different experiences
as I said a moment ago I experience a
red coat and then I experience a a red
head and then I experience a red fire
engine and now I'm getting my idea of
the red
and now I can combine abstract and
relate and come up with an idea of
redness
that then I could add to my
polar bear by imagination
but that's the ability of the mind to
take little units of experience combine
them
abstract them
synthesize them and come up with all
kinds of complex ideas but the
fundamental Point here is that knowledge
comes initially
through the senses not from the mind
this is the question of the Chicken and
the Egg
and it becomes of great importance in
the next 100 years or so from the time
of locks
analysis of it as we will see in later
sessions